Good morning everybody.
صباح الخير للجميع.
I'd like to talk about a couple of things today.
أريد الحديث عن عدة أشياء اليوم.
The first thing is water.
الشئ الأول هو الماء.
Now I see you've all been enjoying the water
الآن أرى أنكم جميعاً تستمتعون بالماء
that's been provided for you here at the conference,
الذي يقدم لكم هنا في المؤتمر،
over the past couple of days.
خلال الأيام القليلة الماضية.
And I'm sure you'll feel that it's from a safe source.
وأنا متأكد أنكم تحسون أنها من مصدر آمن.
But what if it wasn't?
لكن ماذا إن لم تكن كذلك؟
What if it was from a source like this?
ماذا إن كانت من مصدر مثل هذا؟
Then statistics would actually say
عندها ستقول الإحصاء في الواقع
that half of you would now be suffering
أن نصفكم كان سيعاني
with diarrhea.
من الإسهال.
I talked a lot in the past about statistics,
تحدثت كثيراً في الماضي عن الإحصائيات،
and the provision of safe drinking water for all.
وتوفير مياه الشرب النظيفة للجميع.
But they just don't seem to get through.
لكن لا يبدو أننا وصلنا لذلك.
And I think I've worked out why.
وأعتقد أنني عرفت لماذا.
It's because, using current thinking,
ذلك بسبب، إستخدام نمط التفكير الحالي،
the scale of the problem
حجم المشكلة
just seems too huge to contemplate solving.
يبدو ضخم جداً للتفكير في حلها.
So we just switch off:
لذا فقد توقفنا فقط.
us, governments and aid agencies.
نحن، الحكومات، ووكالات الغوث.
Well, today, I'd like to show you
حسناً، اليوم، أريد أن أعرض عليكم
that through thinking differently,
ذلك عبر التفكير بطريقة مختلفة،
the problem has been solved.
لقد تم حل المشكلة.
By the way, since I've been speaking,
بالمناسبة، منذ بدأت الحديث،
another 13,000 people around the world
ثلاثة عشر ألف شخص حول العالم
are suffering now with diarrhea.
يعانون الآن من الإسهال.
And four children have just died.
ومات بالفعل أربعة أطفال.
I invented Lifesaver bottle
لقد ابتكرت زجاجة منقذة للحياة
because I got angry.
لأنني غضبت.
I, like most of you, was sitting down, the day after Christmas in 2004,
أنا، مثل معظمكم، كنت جالس، بعد يوم من عيد الكريسماس عام 2004،
when I was watching the devastating news
عندما كنت أشاهد الأخبار المدمرة
of the Asian tsunami as it rolled in,
للتسونامي الآسيوي حيث بدأ في التمدد،
playing out on TV.
شاهدته على التلفاز.
The days and weeks that followed,
الايام والأسابيع التي أعقبت ذلك،
people fleeing to the hills,
يهرب الناس الى التلال،
being forced to drink contaminated water
مجبرين على شرب المياة الملوثة،
or face death.
أو مواجهة الموت.
That really stuck with me.
لقد بقي ذلك معاً حقاً.
Then, a few months later,
بعد ذلك، شهور قليلة لاحقاً،
Hurricane Katrina slammed into the side of America.
ضرب إعصار كاترينا جزء من أمريكا.
"Okay," I thought, "here's a First World country, let's see what they can do."
"حسناً"، فكرت، " هنا في العالم المتقدم، لنرى ماذا يمكنهم فعله."
Day one: nothing.
اليوم الأول: لا شئ.
Day two: nothing.
اليوم الثاني: لا شئ.
Do you know it took five days to get water to the Superdome?
هل تعلمون أنه أستغرق خمسة أيام لتصل المياة الى سوبردوم؟
People were shooting each other on the streets
كان الناس يقتلون بعضهم البعض في الطرق،
for TV sets and water.
لأجل التلفاز والمياة.
That's when I decided I had to do something.
بعد ذلك قررت أن علي فعل شئ.
Now I spent a lot of time in my garage, over the next weeks and months,
الآن قضيت وقتاً طويلاً في مرآبي، خلال الاسابيع والشهور التي أعقبت ذلك.
and also in my kitchen -- much to the dismay of my wife. (Laughter)
وأيضاً في مطبخي، ما أثار إستياء زوجتي.
However, after a few failed prototypes,
لكن، بعد نماذج قليلة فاشلة،
I finally came up with this, the Lifesaver bottle.
توصلت أخيراً لهذا، الزجاجة المنقذة للحياة.
Okay, now for the science bit.
حسناً، الآن قليل من العلوم.
Before Lifesaver, the best hand filters were only capable
قبل منقذ الحياة، كان بمقدور أفضل الفلاتر فقط
of filtering down to about 200 nanometers.
أن يصفي الى حوالي مئتان نانومتر.
The smallest bacteria is about 200 nanometers.
أصغر أنواع البكتريا حجمها حوالي مئتان نانومتر.
So a 200-nanometer bacteria
لذا فمئتان نانومتر باكتيريا
is going to get through a 200-nanometer hole.
ستعبر من فتحة حجمها مئتان نانو متر.
The smallest virus, on the other hand,
أصغر الفيروسات، على الجانب الآخر،
is about 25 nanometers.
حوالي خمسة وعشرين نانومتر.
So that's definitely going to get through those 200 nanometer holes.
إذاً من المؤكد أن يعبر ذلك عبر تلك الفتحة التي حجمها مئتان نانومتر.
Lifesaver pores are 15 nanometers.
مسام منقذ الحياة هي خمسة عشر نانومتر.
So nothing is getting through.
لذا فلن يمر شئ عبره.
Okay, I'm going to give you a bit of a demonstration.
حسناً، سأقوم بتقديم تمهيد صغير لذلك.
Would you like to see that?
هل تريدون متابعة ذلك؟
I spent all the time setting this up, so I guess I should.
لقد قضيت كل الأوقات أجهز لهذا. لذا أعتقد أن علي فعل ذلك.
We're in the fine city of Oxford.
نحن في مدينة أوكسفورد الجيدة.
So -- someone's done that up.
لذا-- فقد جهّز أحدهم ذلك.
Fine city of Oxford, so what I've done is I've gone
مدينة أوكسفورد الجيدة، إذاً ما فعلته أنني ذهبت وجلبت بعض الماء
and got some water from the River Cherwell,
من نهر تشيرول،
and the River Thames,
ونهر ثامس،
that flow through here. And this is the water.
اللذان ينسابان هنا. وهذه هي المياة.
But I got to thinking, you know,
لكنني فكرت، تعرفون،
if we were in the middle of a flood zone
اذا كنت في وسط منطقة فيضان
in Bangladesh, the water wouldn't look like this.
في بنغلاديش، لن يبدو الماء كهذا.
So I've gone and got some stuff to add into it.
لذا ذهبت وجلبت بعض الأشياء الأخرى لإضافتها معها.
And this is from my pond.
وهذه بِركة من وجهة نظري .
(Sniffs) (Coughs) Have a smell of that, mister cameraman.
(شم) (سعال) لديها رائحة ذلك، سيدي المصور.
Okay. (Laughs) Right.
حسناً. (ضحك) حسناً.
We're just going to pour that in there.
سنقوم بوضع ذلك هناك.
Audience: Ugh!
الحضور: مقرف!
Michael Pritchard: Okay. We've got some runoff
مايكل: حسناً. تحصلنا على بعض الجريان
from a sewage plant farm.
من محطة للصرف الصحي في المزرعة.
So I'm just going to put that in there.
إذاً سأقوم بوضع ذلك هناك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Put that in there. There we go.
أضعها هنا. ها نحن نمضي.
And some other bits and pieces, chuck that in there.
وبعض الأجزاء والقطع الأخرى، أخلطها هناك.
And I've got a gift here from a friend of mine's rabbit.
وتحصلت على هدية من أرنب صديق لي.
So we're just going to put that in there as well.
إذاً سنقوم بوضع ذلك هناك أيضاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Okay. (Laughter) Now.
حسناً. (ضحك) الآن.
The Lifesaver bottle works really simply.
الزجاجة المنقذة للحياة تعمل ببساطة جداً.
You just scoop the water up.
أنت تغرف الماء فيها.
Today I'm going to use a jug
اليوم سأقوم بإستخدام الإبريق
just to show you all. Let's get a bit of that poo in there.
فقط لأعرض عليكم جميعاً. لنأخذ قليلاً من ذلك البراز هناك.
That's not dirty enough. Let's just stir that up a little bit.
هذا ليس متسخاً بما يكفي. لنحرك ذلك قليلاً.
Okay, so I'm going to take this really filthy water,
حسناً، سأقوم بأخذ تلك المياة القذرة فعلاً،
and put it in here. Do you want a drink yet?
وأضعها هنا. هل تريدون شربها؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Okay. There we go.
حسناً. لنواصل.
Replace the top.
تبديل إتجاهها.
Give it a few pumps. Okay?
نقوم برجّها قليلاً. حسناً؟
That's all that's necessary.
هذا كل شئ ضروري.
Now as soon as I pop the teat,
الآن بمجرد أن أفتح هذه الحلمة،
sterile drinking water is going to come out.
ستخرج مياة شرب معقمة. يجب أن أكون سريعاً.
I've got to be quick. Okay, ready?
حسناً، جاهزون؟
There we go. Mind the electrics.
لنواصل. أحذروا الكهرباء.
That is safe, sterile drinking water.
هذا مأمون، مياة شرب معقمة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Cheers.
ابتهاج.
There you go Chris.
كريس هيا لتجرب .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
What's it taste of?
كيف تبدو نكهتها؟
Chris Anderson: Delicious.
كريس أندرسون: شهية.
Michael Pritchard: Okay.
مايكل: حسناً.
Let's see Chris's program throughout the rest of the show. Okay?
لنراقب برنامج كريس خلال ما تبقى من العرض. حسناً؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Okay. Lifesaver bottle is used by thousands of people around the world.
حسناً. زجاجة منقذ الحياة يتسخدمها آلالاف الناس حول العالم.
It'll last for 6,000 liters.
فترة صلاحيتها بعد ستة آلالاف لتراً.
And when it's expired, using failsafe technology,
وعندما تنتهي الصلاحية، بإستخدام تكنلوجيا مأمونة الجانب،
the system will shut off, protecting the user.
سيقوم النظام بالإغلاق، لحماية مستخدمها.
Pop the cartridge out. Pop a new one in.
أسحب الخرطوش خارجاً. قم بإحلاله بآخر جديد.
It's good for another 6,000 liters.
أنها جاهزة لستة آلالاف لتراً أخرى.
So let's look at the applications.
إذاً لنلقي نظرة على تطبيقاتها.
Traditionally, in a crisis, what do we do?
تقليدياً في الكوارث، ماذا نفعل؟
We ship water.
نشحن مياة.
Then, after a few weeks, we set up camps.
بعد ذلك، بعد أسابيع قليلة، نقوم بتشييد مخيمات.
And people are forced to come into the camps to get their safe drinking water.
ويجبر الناس على المجئ للمخيمات للحصول على مياة شرب نقية.
What happens when 20,000 people congregate in a camp?
ماذا يحدث عندما يحتشد عشرين الف شخص في مخيم؟
Diseases spread. More resources are required.
تنتشر الأمراض. ونحتاج لموارد أكثر.
The problem just becomes self-perpetuating.
تصبح المشكلة معيدة لإنتاج نفسها.
But by thinking differently,
لكن بالتفكير بطريقة مغايرة،
and shipping these,
وشحن هذه،
people can stay put.
يمكن للناس البقاء حيث هم.
They can make their own sterile drinking water,
يمكنهم عمل مياة شربهم النقية بأنفسهم،
and start to get on with rebuilding their homes and their lives.
ويبدأون في إعادة تشييد منازلهم وحياتهم مجدداً.
Now, it doesn't require a natural disaster
الآن، لا تتطلب كارثة طبيعية
for this to work.
لهذا لتعمل.
Using the old thinking, of national infrastructure
بإستخدام التفكير القديم، للبنية التحتية القومية،
and pipe work, is too expensive.
وعمل المجاري، هذا مكلّف جداً.
When you run the numbers on a calculator,
عندما تحسب الأرقام على الحاسبات،
you run out of noughts.
ستنتهي أوراقك.
So here is the "thinking different" bit.
إذاً هنا قطعة "تفكير مغاير".
Instead of shipping water,
بدلاً عن شحن المياة،
and using man-made processes to do it,
وإستخدام عملية معالجة بواسطة الأيدي لفعلها،
let's use Mother Nature. She's got a fantastic system.
لنستخدم الطبيعة الأم. إن لديها نظام رائع.
She picks the water up from there,
فهي تأخذ الماء من هناك،
desalinates it, for free, transports it over there,
تقوم بتحليته، مجاناً، تنقله الى هناك،
and dumps it onto the mountains, rivers, and streams.
وتقلبه على الجبال، الأنهار، والجداول.
And where do people live? Near water.
وأين نعيش نحن؟ قرب الماء.
All we've go to do
كل ما علينا فعله
is make it sterile. How do we do that?
هو جعل الماء نقياً.
Well, we could use the Lifesaver bottle.
حسناً، يمكننا إستخدام زجاجة منقذ الحياة.
Or we could use one of these.
أو يمكننا إستخدام واحدة من تلك.
The same technology, in a jerry can.
نفس التكنلوجيا، في تنك.
This will process 25,000 liters of water;
سيقوم هذا بمعالجة 25 ألف لتر من الماء.
that's good enough for a family of four,
هذا جيد جداً لأسرة مكونة من أربعة أشخاص،
for three years.
لمدة ثلاثة أعوام.
And how much does it cost?
وكم يكلف هذا؟
About half a cent a day to run.
حوالي نصف سنت يومياً للتشغيل.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, by thinking differently, and processing water
إذاً، بالتفكير بطرق مغايرة، ومعالجة المياة
at the point of use,
عند الإستخدام،
mothers and children no longer have to walk four hours a day
لن يتحتم على الأمهات والأطفال السير لأربع ساعات يومياً
to collect their water.
لجلب الماء.
They can get it from a source nearby.
يمكنهم الحصول عليه من أي مصدر قريب منهم.
So with just eight billion dollars,
إذاً بثمانية بلايين دولار فقط،
we can hit the millennium goal's target
يمكننا الوصول الى هدف الألفية
of halving the number of people
والمتمثل في خفض عدد الاشخاص
without access to safe drinking water.
الذين لا يحصلون على مياة شرب آمنة.
To put that into context,
لوضع ذلك في السياق،
The U.K. government spends about 12 billion pounds
تنفق حكومة المملكة المتحدة حوالي 12 بليون جنيه
a year on foreign aid.
سنوياً على المساعدات الخارجية.
But why stop there?
لكن لماذا نتوقف هناك؟
With 20 billion dollars, everyone can have access to safe drinking water.
بعشرين بليون دولار، يمكن لأي شخص الحصول على مياة شرب آمنة.
So the three-and-a-half billion people
إذاً الثلاثة بلايين ونصف شخص
that suffer every year as a result,
الذين يعانون سنوياً، كنتيجة لذلك،
and the two million kids that die every year,
والأثنين مليون طفل الذين يموتون سنوياً،
will live.
سيعيشون.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)